# Crystal Yan 408.899.9671 | yan.crystal.c@gmail.com

User experience (UX) and product leader focused on transforming high-impact organizations with human-centered design (HCD). Experience using behavioral science and machine learning to create meaningful experiences for B2B and B2C products globally.

## **EXPERIENCE**

# **Senior Product & UX Consultant** — U.S. Digital Service, Washington, DC

OCT 2017 - PRESENT

- · Serving a tour of duty with USDS (usds.gov), a startup within the federal government using design and technology to deliver better government services to the American people.
- UX Lead (Feb 2018-Present) Conducting user research for a product development team to understand how changes to a Medicare payments system will affect providers and beneficiaries.
- UX Lead (Mar-Apr 2018) Visualized policy and technology systems for a discovery sprint to uncover barriers to adoption for electronic prescription of controlled substances and to investigate the role of technology in the opioids crisis.
- UX Lead (Jan-Feb 2018) Journey mapped the experience of health tech startups and researchers and presented policy change recommendations to CMS Administrator for a discovery sprint to uncover ways to improve access to Medicare and Medicaid data.
- Group Product Manager (Nov 2017-Jan 2018) Coached six product managers on UX success metrics and data-informed decision-making for the launch of the submissions experience of the Quality Payments Program (qpp.cms.gov), which constitutes 4% of the US's GDP.

# **Product Advisor & Career Coach** — Independent, *Remote*

AUG 2016-PRESENT

- UX Lead for MyHealthEd, Inc, a startup nonprofit transforming sex education with storytelling. Contributed to raising \$50K in funding and launching beta product by leading the UX research and design for Real Talk, an app co-designed with 13-14 year old low-income teens in rural areas.
- Career Coach for a California College of the Arts MBA in Design Strategy student.
- Product Consultant for a fintech startup launching a high interest consumer bank account.
- Instructional Design Consultant for the DC Mayor's Office Summer Youth Employment Program; developed curriculum to teach an introduction to UX design for high school students.
- · Communication Design Lead for Rise, part of team that passed Survivors' Bill of Rights Act in seven state legislatures and in Congress - unanimously in the US Senate & US House.

# **Senior Product Manager & UX Designer** — FiscalNote, Washington, DC

AUG 2015 - OCT 2017

(Promoted from Associate PM to PM in March 2016, from PM to Senior PM in September 2017)

- Doubled product team in headcount and reduced ramp-up time for new hires by 50% by developing interviewing guides and onboarding program; report directly to COO/VP of Product.
- Led training workshops for team: "Intro to UX Research" and "Design for Non-Designers"
- · Contributed to landing first enterprise client with total contract value that grew company revenue by 9% by setting vision and roadmap of multimillion dollar product portfolio, and setting vision for launching new EU, South America, and Asia product lines for web and mobile.
- Designed new features and product lines that grew average contract value (ACV) 43.54% from 2015 Q4 to 2016 Q3 by leading the full-stack design discovery process (lead design sprints, conduct qualitative and quantitative user experience (UX) research with interviews and metrics analysis; lead ideation and wireframing; create interactive high-fidelity prototypes, and test with users to validate hypotheses), leading delivery sprints with engineering and QA, and planning and executing on go-to-market strategy with marketing, sales, and client success teams.
- · Launched company's first iOS app in four months with one engineer by producing hi-fidelity prototypes, running usability testing and beta testing, and iterating based on user feedback.
- · Aligned executive team (heads of product, sales, client success, and marketing) by developing user personas that guide product strategy, marketing campaign targeting, and sales strategy.
- Improved site performance and remove user interface (UI) inconsistencies and lines of legacy code by developing the first style guide, UI asset and UX pattern library.

# **Business Development** — FiscalNote, Washington, DC

AUG 2014 - AUG 2015

· Contributed to company raising \$18 million by consistently exceeding sales quotas and closing \$386,842 in new revenue (34% of company revenue) from new clients (Uber, Lyft, Coinbase) with shortest sales cycles. Grew ACV by 76.82% by leading and developing training for 35+ new hires on structuring pricing and contracts to maximize ACV and improve cash flow.

#### **SKILLS**

### Management:

Interviewing, Hiring, Training, Leading **Design Sprints** User Research: Data Analysis, Contextual Inquiry, User Testing Design: Interaction, UI & Visual (Sketch, Adobe CS), Mobile,

Prototyping (InVision)

## **SPEAKING**

The Lead Developer London, UK O'Reilly Fluent 2018 San Jose, CA **Code for America** Oakland, CA Data Day (keynote) Mexico City, Mexico StarsConf 2017 Santiago, Chile SeleniumConf 2017 Berlin, Germany **Grace Hopper 2017** Orlando, FL Microsoft Research Beijing, China

## **AWARDS**

McKinsey & Co. **NGWL 2017** 

## **EDUCATION**

**Amherst College** BA, Economics **Tsinghua University** International Affairs Beijing, China **International Honors Program** Urban Planning & Anthropology NYC, Delhi, Dakar, **Buenos Aires**